It is very fashionable and proper to speak about food
يعد التحدث عن الطعام أمر لائق و طبيعي
in all its forms, all its colors, aromas and tastes.
بجميع ألونه و أشكاله و بمختلف النكهات.
But after the food goes through the digestive system,
ولكن بعد المرور الطعام خلال الجهاز الهضمي،
it is no longer fashionable to speak about it.
لن يعود التحدث عنه أمراً لائقاً.
It is rather revolting.
بل سيصبح الأمر مقززاً.
I'm a guy who has graduated from bullshit to full-shit.
أنا رجلٌ تخلص من روث البقر ليقع في روثٍ أخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My organization, Gram Vikas, which means "village development organization,"
منظمتي، جرام فيكاس، تعني "منظمة إنماء القرى"
was working in the area of renewable energy.
عملت في مجال الطاقة المتجددة.
On the most part, we were producing biogas,
في الغالب كنا نقوم بإنتاج الغاز الحيوي،
biogas for rural kitchens.
للمطابخ في الأرياف.
We produce biogas in India by using animal manure,
في الهند، يتم إنتاج الغاز من روث الحيوانات
which usually, in India, is called cow dung.
غالباً ما نسميه في الهند روث الأبقار.
But as the gender-sensitive person that I am,
ولأنني متحيز للرجال
I would like to call it bullshit.
فأفضل أن أسميه روث الثيران.
But realizing later on
بعد أن أدركنا فيما بعد أهمية
we went into the arena of sanitation.
ذهبنا إلى محطة التنقية ومعالجة المياه.
Eighty percent of all diseases in India and most developing countries
وجدنا أن 80% من الأمراض في الهند
And when we look at the reason for poor quality water,
وعندما نبحث عن سبب هذا التدني،
you find that it is our abysmal attitude to the disposal of human waste.
نجد أنها طريقتنا الخاطئة في التخلص من فضلات البشر.
Human waste, in its rawest form,
فضلات البشر بشكلها المعتاد،
finds its way back to drinking water, bathing water, washing water,
تجد طريقها لمياه الشرب والاستحمام والغسيل،
irrigation water, whatever water you see.
و مياه الري وشتى أنواع المياه.
And this is the cause for 80 percent of the diseases in rural areas.
وهذا هو سبب 80% من الأمراض في الأرياف.
In India, it is unfortunately only the women who carry water.
لسوء الحظ، في الهند نقل المياه عملٌ خاص بالنساء
So for all domestic needs, women have to carry water.
لذلك، تنقل النساء الماء لكافة الاحتياجات.
So that is a pitiable state of affairs.
وهذه حالةٌ يرثى لها.
Open defecation is rampant.
قضاء الحاجة في الخارج في تزايد.
Seventy percent of India defecates in the open.
70% من الهنود يقضون حاجاتهم في الخلاء.
They sit there out in the open,
يجلسون في الهواء الطلق،
with the wind on their sails,
والرياح تداعب سيقانهم،
hiding their faces, exposing their bases,
يخفون رؤوسهم و يبدون مؤخراتهم،
and sitting there in pristine glory --
ويجلسون متفاخرين بالفطرة--
70 percent of India.
نعم، 70% من الهند.
And if you look at the world total,
وعلى مستوى العالم كاملاً،
60 percent of all the crap that is thrown into the open is by Indians.
60% من البراز في العراء ناتج عن الهنود.
A fantastic distinction.
ياله من امتيازٍ رائع.
I don't know if we Indians can be proud of such a distinction.
لا أعلم إن كان بوسعنا التفاخر بشيءٍ كهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
we began to talk about how to really address this situation of sanitation.
وبدأنا نبحث في كيفية التعامل مع مشكلة التعقيم.
And we came together and formed a project called MANTRA.
واتحدنا و أنشأنا مشروعاً يدعى MANTRA
MANTRA stands for Movement and Action Network for Transformation of Rural Areas.
MANTRA هي إختصار لشبكة التحرك والعمل للنهوض بالأرياف
So we are speaking about transformation, transformation in rural areas.
لذلك، نحن نتحدث عن النهوض بالمناطق الريفية.
Villages that agree to implement this project,
قامت القرى التي وافقت على تطبيق المشروع،
they organize a legal society
بتنظيم مجتمع رسمي
where the general body consists of all members
حيث الدور الأساسي مناط بجميع الأعضاء
who elect a group of men and women who implement the project
الذين ينتخبون مجموعة من الرجال والنساء ليطبقوا المشروع
and, later on, who look after the operation and maintenance.
ويقومون لاحقاً بالعناية بالعمليات و الصيانة.
They decide to build a toilet and a shower room.
قرروا بناءَ مرحاضاً وغرفة استحمام.
And from a protected water source,
تستمد مياهها من مصدر أمن.
water will be brought to an elevated water reservoir and piped to all households
يتم جلب المياه إلى خزان مرتفع وتضخ إلى جميع البيوت
through three taps:
من خلال ثلاثة حنفيات:
one in the toilet, one in the shower, one in the kitchen, 24 hours a day.
موزعة على المرحاض والحمام والمطبخ لمدة 24 ساعة يومياً.
The pity is that our cities, like New Delhi and Bombay,
الأمر المؤسف أن مدناً كنيودلهي و بومباي
do not have a 24-hour water supply.
لا تحظى بالماء لمدة 24 ساعة.
But in these villages, we want to have it.
ولكن سنحصل عليها في هذه القرى.
There is a distinct difference in the quality.
هناك اختلافٌ واضحٌ في الجودة.
Well in India, we have a theory, which is very much accepted
في الهند، لدينا نظرية متقبلة بشكل كبير
by the government bureaucracy and all those who matter,
من قبل الحكومة والبيروقراطية والمسؤولين
that poor people deserve poor solutions
هي أن الفقراء يستحقون حلولاً رديئة
and absolutely poor people deserve pathetic solutions.
والأشخاص الفقراء جداً يستحقون حلولاً مثيرة للشفقة.
This, combined with a Nobel Prize-worthy theory that
إلى جانب مبدأ آخر يستحق جائزة نوبل يقول:
the cheapest is the most economic,
أن الأرخص هو الأكثر توفيراً.
is the heady cocktail that the poor are forced to drink.
هذا هو الشراب المر الذي يجبر الفقراء على شربه
We are fighting against this.
نحن نكافح هذه المبادىء.
We feel that the poor have been humiliated for centuries.
نحن ندرك أن الفقراء يهانون منذ قرون.
And even in sanitation,
حتى فيما يخص الصرف الصحي
they should not be humiliated.
يجب ألا تتم إهانتهم.
Sanitation is more about dignity
لأن الصرف الصحي هو مسألة كرامة،
than about human disposal of waste.
أكثر من كونه مجرد مسألة تخلصٍ من الفضلات.
And so you build these toilets and very often,
لذلك بنينا هذه المراحيض، وكثيراً ما نسمع
And you can see that in front are the attached houses
كما ترون في الأمام منازلهم متصلة ببعضها.
and the others are the toilets.
وفي الجانب الآخر هناك المراحيض.
So these people, without a single exception of a family in a village,
لذلك قرر جميع الأشخاص ومن دون أي استثناء في القرية،
decide to build a toilet, a bathing room.
بناء مرحاضٍ وحمام.
And for that, they come together, collect all the local materials --
ولذلك تعاونوا لجمع المواد اللازمة
local materials like rubble, sand, aggregates,
من القرية كالحجارة والرمل والحصى،
usually a government subsidy is available
عادةً ما تدعم الحكومة على الأقل
like cement, steel, toilet commode.
مثل الإسمنت والصاج ومقعد المرحاض.
And they build a toilet and a bathing room.
ثم يبنون المرحاض و الحمام.
Also, all the unskilled laborers, that is daily wage earners, mostly landless,
كما نعطي عمال المياومة الذين لا يملكون حرفاً والذين لايملكون الأراضي
are given an opportunity to be trained as masons and plumbers.
الفرصة ليصبحوا بنائين و سباكين.
So while these people are being trained, others are collecting the materials.
بينما يتدرب هؤلاء، يقوم الآخرون بجمع المواد.
And when both are ready, they build a toilet, a shower room,
وعندما يكون الطرفان جاهزان، يبنون المرحاض والحمام
and of course also a water tower, an elevated water reservoir.
وكذلك يتم بناء برج ليحمل خزان المياه المرفوع.
We use a system of two leach pits to treat the waste.
نطبق نظاماً لمعالجة الفضلات، يتكون من حفرتين للترشيح
From the toilet, the muck comes into the first leach pit.
تصل فضلات المرحاض إلى الحفرة الأولى.
And when it is full, it is blocked and it can go to the next.
وبامتلاء الأولى تمرر الحفرة الفضلات إلى الأخرى.
But we discovered that if you plant banana trees, papaya trees
ولكننا اكتشفنا أن زراعة أشجار الموز والبابايا
on the periphery of these leach pits,
في محيط حفر الترشيح
they grow very well because they suck up all the nutrients
يحسن من نموها وذلك لأنها تمتص جميع المواد الغذائية
and you get very tasty bananas, papayas.
لنحصل على موز وبابايا لذيذان جداً.
If any of you come to my place,
إذا جاء أحدكم لزيارتي،
I would be happy to share these bananas and papayas with you.
فسأكون سعيداً بتقديم هذه الفواكه له.
This is in a village where most of the people are even illiterate.
ما ترونه أُنجز في قرية أغلب سكانها أُميون.
It is always a 24-hour water supply
تضخ المياه طوال اليوم وعلى الدوام.
because water gets polluted very often when you store it --
لأن المياه تتلوث كلما زادت مدة تخزينها--
a child dips his or her hand into it, something falls into it.
قد يضع طفل يده فيها، أو قد يسقط شيء بداخل الخزان
So no water is stored. It's always on tap.
لذلك لا تُخزن المياه بل تكون دائماً في الحنفية.
This is how an elevated water reservoir is constructed.
هكذا يتم بناء خزان مياه مرتفع.
And that is the end product.
على يمين الشاشة نرى الخزان الجاهز.
Because it has to go high, and there is some space available,
الغاية من ارتفاع البرج هي توفير المساحة
two or three rooms are made under the water tower,
لتجهيز غرفتين أو ثلاثة أسفل برج المياه،
which are used by the village for different committee meetings.
تستخدمها القرية لعقد اجتماعات اللجان المختلفة.
We have had clear evidence of the great impact of this program.
لدينا دليل واضح على التأثير العظيم لهذا البرنامج.
Before we started, there were, as usual,
قبل أن نبدأ كالعادة كان
more than 80 percent of people suffering from waterborne diseases.
أكثر من 80% من الناس يعانون من أمراض تنقلها المياه.
among all these villages -- 1,200 villages have completed it --
القرى الـ 1200 التي أتمت المشروع --
waterborne diseases have come down 82 percent.
نجحنا بتقليص نسبة أمراض المياه إلى 82%.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Women usually used to spend, especially in the summer months,
اعتادت النساء، وخاصة في الصيف، على قضاء
about six to seven hours a day carrying water.
ما يقارب ست إلى سبع ساعات يومياً في نقل الماء.
And when they went to carry water,
وعندما يذهبن لجلب المياه،
because, as I said earlier, it's only women who carry water,
لأنه وكما قلت آنفاً، النساء فقط هن من ينقل المياه.
they used to take their little children, girl children, also to carry water,
اعتدن على أخذ بناتهن أيضاً لجلب المياه.
or else to be back at home to look after the siblings.
أو يبقين في المنزل للعناية بإخوتهن.
So there were less than nine percent of girl children attending school,
لذلك، نسبة البنات الملتحقات بالمدارس أقل من 9%
even if there was a school.
حتى ولو كانت المدرسة متوفرة.
And boys, about 30 percent.
وللصبيان كانت النسبة 30%.
But girls, it has gone to about 90 percent and boys, almost to 100 percent.
أما الآن، صعدت نسبة البنات إلى 90% والصبيان إلى 100% تقريباً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The most vulnerable section in a village
أقل الناس حظاً في القرى.
are the landless laborers who are the daily wage-earners.
هم عمال المياومة من غير مالكي الأراضي.
Because they have gone through this training
و لأنهم خاضوا هذا التدريب
to be masons and plumbers and bar benders,
ليصبحوا بنائين و سباكين و ثنَّائي قضبان.
now their ability to earn has increased 300 to 400 percent.
أما الأن فقدرتهم على جني المال زادت بنسبة 300% إلى 400%
So this is a democracy in action
هذه هي الديمقراطية المفعلة.
because there is a general body, a governing board, the committee.
لأن هنالك قوى عاملة شاملة، وجهة منظمة، ولجنة.
People are questioning, people are governing themselves,
يطلب الناس العلم وينظمون أنفسهَم بأنفُسهم.
people are learning to manage their own affairs,
ويتعلمون إدارة حياتهم بأنفسهم.
they are taking their own futures into their hands.
فهم يمتلكون مستقبلهم بين أيديهم.
And that is democracy at the grassroots level in action.
وهذا يمثل جوهرالديموقراطية على أرض الواقع.
More than 1,200 villages have so far done this.
أكثر من 1200 قرية وصلت لهذه المرحلة حتى الآن.
It benefits over 400,000 people and it's still going on.
ينتفع من المشروع أكثر من 400.000 نسمة والأعداد تتزايد.
For India and such developing countries,
في الهند وغيرها من الدول النامية،
armies and armaments,
الجيوش ومصانع الأسلحة،
software companies and spaceships
شركات البرمجيات وسفن الفضاء.
may not be as important as taps and toilets.
قد لا تتعدى أهميتها أهمية الحنفيات والمراحيض.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
شكراً لكم. شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.